I've got an article in this month's
Silicon Chip Magazine, April 2009,
about
uh this new project I've come up with.
It's really simple. It's called the
microcurrent. And
it's
uh it fixes a major problem to do with
almost every multimeter on the market.
Now, I've really um since I developed
this little project, I've
lost count of the number of people who
have
uh been baffled that their multimeter,
even a
precision Fluke 87 multimeter, uh that
they've been they've been using for 20
years is
in many cases useless at measuring
precision current.
Uh
be it in DC or AC circuits. And it's to
do with burden voltage. Now, every uh
most people know about burden voltage.
There's a There's a shunt resistor
inside that
drops a voltage when you pass current
through it.
No problem. Easy, right? And but most
people think it's really small. But it's
not. The closer you get to the full
scale range of the meter,
the the the bigger the drop, obviously.
Now,
a really good meter, like the Fluke
87-5,
it will have Well, well, this one
actually has 1.8 mV per milliamp
burden voltage. So, if you pass 200
milliamps through this, if you try to
measure 200 milliamps, that's a 360 mV
drop. Now, that it may not sound like
much, but really 360 mV is If your
circuit is 5 V, bingo, you've already uh
thrown your circuit out of voltage spec,
probably. Let alone a 3.3 V circuit. Or
I'm working a lot these days on 1.2 V
circuits. So, it's
a current like this you really can't a
meter like this you really can't measure
precision current with. It's crazy. So,
the micro current is it's it's really
simple. I don't know why anyone really
hasn't done one before. It's
it's just a low value shunt resistor
with a high precision amplifier in it.
And it solves the problem really well.
But, yeah. A lot of people seemed
embarrassed that they don't know
that their meter is not very precise at
all. And that goes for virtually every
meter on the market. There are some that
are almost an order of magnitude worse
than this. And price really doesn't have
much to do with it. You can pay $2,000
for a multimeter and it's still going to
have the same problem. So,
just be wary of it. Burden voltage.